Susan Oberman papers MSS 16349
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
Susan Oberman papers
1960's-2013
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
Oberman, Susan
MSS 16349
5.25 Cubic Feet 11 document boxes 3 audiocassettes, one music album, a textile banner, suffragette armbands, political buttons, posters, and oversize items.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Provenance
Gift from Susan Oberman, 2016.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five series: Series 1. Women's organizations, Series 2. Peace organizations, Series 3. Diversity organizations, Series 4. Publications, and Series 5. Ephemera and audio visual materials
Biographocal Note
Susan Oberman graduated from Goucher College in 1968 with a B.A. degree. She has worked as an activist in movements for social change since the mid-1960's and founded the Nassau County Women's Liberation Center in New York in 1972. She moved to Charlottesville, Virginia in 1988 and became the director of the FOCUS Women's Resource Center. After working at FOCUS for ten years she founded Common Ground Negotiations Services.
Oberman was a founder and planner of the annual Days of Dialogue on Race Relations events held annually in Charlottesville from 1997 to 2002, and was a founding member of the Black Women/White Women/all Women dialogue group.
She has authored several articles including "Confidentiality in Mediation: An Application of The Right To Privacy" and "Mediation Theory vs. Practice: What Are We Really Doing? Re-Solving A Professional Conundrum."
Sources:
"Susan Oberman." LinkedIn, 21 Nov. 2017, https://www.linkedin.com/in/susan-oberman-390a1413.
"Susan Oberman is by temperament and profession, a Mediator." Common Ground Negotiations, 21 Nov. 2017, http://www.commongroundnegotiation.com/index.php/bio.
Scope and Contents Note
Susan Oberman papers (1960's-2013, 5.25 cubic feet) documenting her activism in women's issues in Nassau County, New York (1972-1989) and her support for women, social justice, and race relations in Charlottesville, Virginia (1990-2013). Of interest is information about the history of African American life in Charlottesville including questions about the racial background of Queen Charlotte. There are also three audiocassette tapes related to the Focus Women's Resource Center program, Black Women/White Women/All Women's Day of Dialogue, a folk music album, posters, and ephemera including political buttons, suffragette armbands, and a hand-made textile banner from the Nassau County Women's Liberation Center for a protest at the United States Congress. The papers are grouped into fives series: women's organizations, peace organizations, diversity organizations, publications, and ephemera and audiovisual materials.
race relations -- Virginia -- Charlottesville; Women political activists; Banners; Buttons (information artifacts); Long-playing records
- Women's organizations, 1972-2012; 1; 1.75 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  The Women's organizations include the Nassau County Women's Liberation Center, Redstockings Chicago Women's Liberation Union, Nassau County Coalition for Abused Women, in Nassau, New York and the Focus Women's Resource Center in Charlottesville, Virginia. Topics include consciousness raising, radical feminism, and respect for diversity in women. Of interest is a brief mention of a libel suit involving Gloria Steinem, censorship regarding any possible work that she did for the Central Intelligence Agency, and Redstockings Chicago Women's Liberation Center.
  Nassau County Women's Liberation Center (1972-1989) files containing literature, by-laws, correspondence, and notes about events relating to consciousness raising, and radical feminism. Other topics include rape, abuse, and abortion.
  There are also files from the Focus Women's Resource Center (1990-2012) including procedures, a peer counseling manual, monthly reports, and information about programs such as the Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, and a Young Women's Summer Project.
  Folder Five contains information about a lawsuit involving the Redstockings Chicago Women's Liberation Union, and Random House, regarding a chapter in a book about Gloria Steinem and the Central Intelligence Agency.
  Also included is a personal resume and greeting cards of Susan Oberman.
  - New York Women's Movement organizations, 1972; 1974; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nassau County Women's Liberation Center, 1972; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Nassau County Women's Liberation Center, 1974-1985; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder and one oversize newspaper clipping. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nassau County Coalition for Abused Women, 1977-1982; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Redstockings Chicago Women's Liberation Union, 1972-1988; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Redstockings Chicago Women's Liberation Union, Undated; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Redstockings Chicago Women's Liberation Union on abortion, 1989; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center monthly reports, 1990-1996; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center monthly reports, 1997-2002; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center newsletters and invitations, 1988-1997; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center newsletters and invitations, 1998-2000; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center newsletters and invitations, 2001-2008; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center newspaper clippings, 1990-2012; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center peer counseling manual, 1994; 1997-1998; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center procedures, 1994;1998; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 1995-1997; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 1995-2000; 1; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 1999-2000; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2000; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2000-2001; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2001; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2001; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2002; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2002-2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Day of Dialogue Black Women/White Women, 2004; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center e-mails, 2006; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Young Women's Summer Project, 1997; 0.06 Cubic Feet Two folders. (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center photographs Spring fashion show, 1997; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Personal papers Susan Oberman, 1988; 1998; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Peace organizations, 2000-2008; 2; 0.75 Cubic Feet
  This series contains the papers from the Charlottesville Peace curriculum which is set up by the Democrats for Change to facilitate life skills and character education for school children at Burnley-Moran Elementary School and is sponsored by the Charlottesville Non-Violence Education Council. (2000-2002) Also included are correspondence and newspaper clippings about a local teen suicide and psychological support for students at the school.
  There are also files of the Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice from 2000 to 2008 containing advertisements, notes, articles, and ideas for discussion on many social, political, and economic issues on a national and local level, including the Patriot Act, the Homeland Security Act, marriage laws, crime, selective service, protests on the war against Iraq, war profiteers, oil, impeachment of presidents, prayer, the Middle East, National media and elections, terrorism, immigration and the Fourteenth Amendment, taxes, Wall Street, nuclear energy, climate change, local economic development issues, and the University of Virginia living wage campaign.
  - Peace Curriculum, 2000; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Peace Curriculum Burnley Moran Life Skills Committee, 2001; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Peace Curriculum Burnley Moran Communications Workshop, 2001-2002; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2001-2005; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2001-2008; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder and 3 oversize peace posters. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2002; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2004; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2004; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2005; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2005; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2006; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice, 2007-2008; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice Festivals, 2001-2004; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Charlottesville Center for Peace and Justice July 4th events, 2001-2006; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Community Non-Violence Education Council, 2002; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Diversity organizations, 2002-2013; 3; 1 Cubic Feet
  This series is comprosed of correspondence, meeting minutes, planning notes, and newspaper clippings related to the organization, "Citizens for a United Community" (2002-2004) which is created following an act of racial violence in Charlottesville, Virginia in which ten Charlottesville High School students attack a group of students at the University of Virginia. The organization hosts a successful community event, "Many Races-One Community" on April 12, 2003 and then disbands.
  There are also minutes, programs, and correspondence from the Violence Reduction Action group (2003-2004), another diversity organization established to promote diversity and continue the efforts of the CUC. Included is e-mail correspondence about President John Casteen's appointment of a Diversity Commission at the University of Virginia and comments that the City of Charlottesville feels alienated by the commission.
  "Achievement Gap Forum" papers from 2004 to 2006, contain a report on how schools can close the achievement gap among students of different races and improve all student performance. Included are articles and case studies on poverty and race. The forum is sponsored by the Martin Luther King Celebration Committee. There is information regarding the Martin Luther King Celebration Committee (2004-2005) which is set up to honor Dr. King and support civil rights. Included is a mission statement, articles, event programs, meeting notes, and articles and quotes by Dr. King.
  There is also correspondence and meeting notes for Charlottesville's Dialogue on Race (2010-2013), an organization with goals of teaching Charlottesville's racial history, creation of a public memorial of Vinegar Hill, closure of the achievement gap in schools, and support for the Living Wage Campaign at the University of Virginia.
  Of interest is information on the history of African American life in Charlottesville, the racial background of Queen Charlotte, biographies of important educational and civil rights leaders in Charlottesville from the 18th century to the present, a timeline of Charlottesville's race relations (1700-2003), and a list of African-American businesses located on Main Street and Preston Avenue (before the razing of Vinegar Hill) an on the grounds of the University of Virginia.
  There are also planning notes about upcoming panels, speeches, and articles about race and social justice presented by family members, scholars and activists including Dr. Ervin Jordan, Bob Vernon, Gayle Schulman, Shirley Parrish, Scott French, David Swanson and many others. Topics mentioned are the Civil War, segregation, Jim Crow laws, and school desegregation.
  - Citizens for a United Community: Many Races-One Community, 2002-2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Citizens for a United Community: Many Races-One Community, 2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Citizens for a United Community: Many Races-One Community, 2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Citizens for a United Community: Many Races-One Community, 2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Citizens for a United Community: Many Races-One Community, 2003; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Citizens for a United Community: Violence Reduction Action Group, 2003-2004; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Achievement Gap Committee, 2004-2005; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Achievement Gap Committee, 2005; 3; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Martin Luther King Celebration Committee, 2004-2005; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Charlottesville's Dialogue on Race, 2010; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dialogue on Race: History and Culture Action Team, 2009-2012; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Dialogue on Race: History and Culture Action Team, 2012-2013; 3; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Dialogue on Race: History and Tourism Action Team, 2009-2011; 3; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Dialogue on Race: History and Tourism Action Team, 2011; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Piedmont Coucil of the Arts Storyline Project, 2010; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Publications, 1960-2013; 4; 1.5 Cubic Feet 3 document boxes
  This series is composed of many publications including five by Susan Oberman (Pepperdine Dispute Resolution Law Journal, and the Ohio State Journal on Dispute Resolution). Most of the publications address women's issues including marriage, daycare, divorce, sexual relations, abuse, Title IX, birth control, housework, family, salary, lesbianism, strikes, and leadership. Titles include "The Liberated Grapevine of the Women's Liberation Center of Nassau County", "Myth of Women's Inferiority", "Notes New York Radical Women", "Sharing", "Women, A Journal of Liberation", "Women Workers", "The Women of the Telephone Company", "Iris, A Journal about Women", "Lillith, The Jewish Women's Magazine", "The Woman's Place is at the Typewriter", "Counter planning from the Kitchen", "Marxist Approach Problems of Women's Liberation", "Sex Roles and Female Oppression", and "A Women's Touch."
  Authors include Dana Densmore, Evelyn Reed, Roxanne Dunbar, Margery Davis, Alice de Rivera, Ilene Winkler, Voltairine de Cleyre, Sylvia Federici, and many others.
  - The Liberated Grapevine of the Women's Liberation Center of Nassau County, 1972-1983; 4; .030 Cubic Feet 10 folders. (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
    The Liberated Grapevine of the Women's Liberation Center is a complete set of issues for 1976. 1977 and 1978 are just missing March. 1979 is complete except for July. 1980 has all but April and November, and 1983 does not have September-December.
  - Meeting Ground, 1977-1978; 4; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Meeting Ground, 1979-1982; 4; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - New England Free Press, 1954; 1966-1970; undated; 4; 0.06 Cubic Feet Two folders. (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Notes New York Radical Women, 1968; 1970; 4; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Susan Oberman publications, Undated; 4; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets and articles, 1968-2002; 4; 0.06 Cubic Feet Two folders. (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Pamphlets, 1971-1988; 4; 0.06 Cubic Feet Two folders. (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Pamphlets/books (All Work and No Pay), 1975; 4; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Redstockings Feminist Revolution, 1975; 1979; 4; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Women A Journal of Liberation, 1970-1971; 4; 0.06 Cubic Feet Two folders. (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - The Mothers' Book edited by Ronnie Friedland and Carol Kort, 1981; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Ephemera and audio visual materials, 1971-2004; 5; 0.25 Cubic Feet 1 half width document box
  - MoveOn's 50 Ways to Love Your Country, 2004; 0.03 Cubic Feet Book and 4 compact disc audiobook. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Focus Women's Resource Center Black Women/White Women audiocassettes, 1997; 2002-2003; 5; 0.03 Cubic Feet One folder of three audiocassettes made during the Black Women/White Women event at Focus. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Women's Liberation Center of Nassau County textile banner, 1971-1983
  - Suffragette armbands and political buttons (Mondale for president), 1984; Undated
  - The Work of the Women music album, 1975